7 For some reason or other, the house was crowded that night, and the fat Jew
manager who met them at the door was beaming from ear to ear with an oily
tremulous smile. He escorted them to their box with a sort of pp us humility,
waving his fat jeweled hands and talking at the top of his voice. Dorian Gray
loathed him more than ever. He felt as if he had come to look for Miranda and had
been met by Caliban. Lord Henry, upon the other hand, rather liked him. At least he
declared he did, and insisted on shaking him by the hand and assuring him that he
was proud to meet a man who had discovered a real genius and gone bankrupt over a poet
hallwood amused himself with watching the faces in the pit. The heat was
terribly oppressive, and the huge sunlight flamed like a monstrous Dalia
with petals of yellow fire. The youths in the gallery had taken off their coats
and waste coats and hung them over the side. They talked to each other across
the theater and shared their oranges with the Torry girls who sat beside them.
Some women were laughing in the pit.
Their voices were horribly shrill and discordant.
The sound of the popping of corks came from the bar. “What a place to find one’s
divinity in!” said Lord Henry. “Yes!” answered Dorian Gray. “It was here I found her, and
she is divine beyond all living things.
When she acts, you will forget everything.
These common rough people, with their coarse faces and brutal gestures, become
quite different when she's on the stage.
They sit silently and watch her. They weep and laugh as she wills them to do.
She makes them as responsive as a violin.
She spiritualizes them, and one feels that they are of the same flesh and blood as
ones The same flesh and blood as oneself Oh, I hope not!” exclaimed Lord Henry, who
was scanning the occupant of the gallery through his opera glass Don’t pay any attention to him,
Dorian,” said the painter. “I understand what you mean, and I believe in this girl
anyone you love must be marvelous and any girl who has the effect you describe
must be fine and noble. To spiritualize one’s age— —that is something worth doing.
If this girl can give a soul to those who have lived without one, if she can
create the sense of beauty in people whose lives have been sorted and ugly, if
she can strip them of their selfishness and lend them tears for sorrows that are
not their own, she is worthy of all your adoration, worthy of the adoration of the world.
This marriage is quite right. I did not think so at first, but I admit it now. The
gods made cibil vain for you. Without her you would have been
incomplete.” “Thanks, Basil,” answered Dorian Gray, pressing his hand. “I knew that you
would understand me. Harry is so cynical, he terrifies me. But here is the
orchestra. It is quite dreadful, but it only lasts for about 5 minutes. Then the
Cur rises, and you will see the girl to whom I'm going to give all my life, to
whom I've given everything that is good in me.” A quarter of an hour afterwards,
amidst an extraordinary turmoil of applause cibil vain stepped onto the
stage. Yes, she was certainly lovely to look at— —one of the loveliest creatures,
Lord Henry thought, that he had ever seen. There was something of the fa in
her shy grace and startled eyes.
A faint blush, like the shadow of a rose in a mirror of silver, came to her cheeks
as she glanced at the crowded enthusiastic house. She stepped back a
few paces and her lips seemed to tremble.
Basil hallwood leapt to his feet and began to applaud. Motionless, and as one in a dream,
sat Dorian Gray, gazing at her. Lord Henry peered through his glasses, murmuring,
“Charming! charming!” The scene was the hall of Capulet’s
house, and Romeo in his pilgrim’s dress had entered with mausio and his other
friends. The band, such as it was, struck up a few bars of music, and the dance
began. Through the crowd of ungainly, shabbily dressed actors cibil vain moved
like a creature from a finer world. Her body swayed, while she danced, as a plant
sways in the water. The curves of her throat were the curves of a white lily.
Her hands seemed to be made of cool ivory. Yet she was curiously
listless. She showed no sign of joy when her eyes rested on Romeo. The few words
she had to speak— Good pilgrim, you do wrong your hand too much, Which manly devotion shows
in this; For saints have hands that pilgrims’ hands do touch, And palm to palm is holy Palmer's
kiss— with the brief dialogue that follows, were spoken in a thoroughly artificial
manner. The voice was exquisite, but from the point of view of tone it was
absolutely false. It was wrong in color It took away all the life from the verse.
It made the passion unreal. Dorian Gray grew pale as he watched her. He was puzzled and
anxious. Neither of his friends dared to say anything to him. She seemed to them
to be absolutely incompetent. They were horribly disappointed. Yet they felt that the true
test of any Juliet is the balcony scene of the second act. They waited for that.
If she failed there, there was nothing in her. She looked charming as she came out
in the moonlight. That could not be denied. But the staginess of her acting
was unbearable, and grew worse as she went on. Her gestures became absurdly
artificial. She overemphasized everything that she had to say. The beautiful
passage— Thou knowest the mask of night is on my face Elsa would a maiden blush
be paint my cheek For that which thou hast heard me speak tonight was declaimed with the
painful precision of a school girl who has been taught to recite by some second
rate professor of elocution. When she leaned over the balcony and came to those wonderful
lines— Although I joy in thee, I have no joy of this contract tonight It is too
rash, too unadvised, too sudden; Too like the lightning, which doth cease to be a
one can say, “It lightens.” Sweet good night This bud of love by summer’s ripening
breath May prove a beautious flower when next we meet— she spoke the words as though they
conveyed no meaning to her. It was not nervousness. Indeed, so far from being
nervous, she was absolutely self-contained.
It was simply bad art. She was a complete failure. Even the common uneducated
audience of the pit and gallery lost their interest in the play. They got
restless, and began to talk loudly and to whistle. The Jew manager, who was standing
at the back of the dress Circle stamped and swore with rage. The only person
unmoved was the girl herself. When the second act was over,
there came a storm of hisses, and Lord Henry got up from his chair and put on
his coat. “She is quite beautiful, Dorian,” he said, “but she can’t act. Let us
go I'm going to see the play through,” answered the lad, in a hard bitter voice
I'm awfully sorry that I've made you waste an evening, Harry. I apologize to you
both.” “My dear Dorian, I should think Miss vain was ill,” interrupted hallwood We
will come some other night.” “I wish she were ill,” he rejoined joined But she
seems to me to be simply callous and cold. She has entirely altered. Last night
she was a great artist. This evening she is merely a commonplace mediocre
actress.” “Don’t talk like that about anyone you love, Dorian. Love is a more
wonderful thing than art.” “They are both simply forms of
imitation,” remarked Lord Henry. “But do let us go. Dorian, you must not stay here any
longer. It is not good for what morals to see bad acting. Besides, I don’t suppose
you will want your wife to act, so what does it matter if she plays Juliet like
a wooden doll she's very lovely, and if she knows as little about life as she
does about acting, she will be a delightful experience. There are only two kinds of
people who are really fascinating— —people who know absolutely everything, and
people who know absolutely nothing. Good heavens, my dear boy, don’t look so tragic!
The secret of remaining young is never to have an emotion that is unbecoming.
Come to the club with Basil and myself.
We will smoke cigarettes and drink to the beauty of cibil Van She is beautiful.
What more can you want?” “Go away, Harry,” cried the lad. “I want
to be alone. Basil, you must go. Ah! can’t you see that my heart is breaking?” The
hot tears came to his eyes. His lips trembled, and rushing to the back of the
box, he leaned up against the wall, hiding his face in his
hands. “Let us go, Basil,” said Lord Henry with a strange tenderness in his voice,
and the two young men passed out together. A few moments afterwards the
foot lights flared up and the curton rose on the third act. Dorian Gray went
back to his seat. He looked pale, and proud, and indifferent. The play dragged on, and seemed
interminable. Half of the audience went out, tramping in heavy boots and laughing.
The whole thing was a fiasco The last act was played to almost empty benches.
The curtain went down on a titter and some groans. As soon as it was over, Dorian
Gray rushed behind the scenes into the Green Room The girl was standing there
alone, with a look of triumph on her face.
Her eyes were lit with an exquisite fire.
There was a radiance about her. Her parted lips were smiling over some
secret of their own. When he entered, she looked at him, and an expression of
infinite joy came over her. “How badly I acted tonight Dorian!” she cried. “Horribly!”
he answered, gazing at her in amazement.
“Horribly! It was dreadful. Are you ill? You have no idea what it was. You have no
idea what I suffered.” The girl smiled.
“Dorian,” she answered, lingering over his name with long drawn music in her voice,
as though it were sweeter than honey to the red petals of her mouth. “Dorian, you should have
understood. But you understand now, don’t you?” “Understand what?” he asked, angrily. “Why
I was so bad tonight Why I shall always be bad. Why I shall never act well
again.” He shrugged his shoulders. “You are ill, I suppose. When you are ill you
shouldn’t act. You make yourself ridiculous. My friends were bored. I was
bored.” She seemed not to listen to him.
She was transfigured with joy. An ecstasy of happiness dominated her.
“Dorian, Dorian,” she cried, “before I knew you, acting was the one reality of my
life. It was only in the theater that I lived. I thought that it was all true. I
was Rosalind one night and Porsche the other. The joy of beatric was my joy, and
the sorrows of Cordelia were mine also. I believed in everything. The common people
who acted with me see seemed to me to be godlike. The painted scenes were my world.
I knew nothing but shadows, and I thought them real. You came— —oh, my beautiful love!—
!—and you freed my soul from prison. You taught me what reality really is tonight
for the first time in my life, I saw through the holess the sham, the
silliness of the empty pageant in which I had always played tonight for the
first time, I became conscious that the Romo was hideous, and old, and painted,
that the moonlight in the orchard was false, that the scenery was vulgar, and
that the words I had to speak were unreal, were not my words, were not what I
wanted to say. You had brought me something higher, something of which all art is but a
reflection. You had made me understand what love really is. My love! My love! Prince Charming!
Prince of life!
I have grown sick of shadows. You are more to me than all art can ever be. What
have I to do with the puppets of a play? When I came on tonight I could not
understand how it was that everything had gone from me. I thought that I was
going to be wonderful. I found that I could do nothing. Suddenly it dawned on my soul
what it all meant. The knowledge was exquisite to me. I heard them hissing, and
I smiled. What could they know of love such as ours? Take me away, Dorian— —take me
away with you, where we can be quite alone. I hate the stage. I might mimic a
passion that I do not feel, but I cannot mimic one that burns me like fire. Oh,
Dorian, Dorian, you understand now what it signifies? Even if I could do it, it would
be profanation for me to play at being in love. You have made me see
that.” He flung himself down on the sofa and and turned away his
face. “You have killed my love,” he muttered. She looked at him in wonder and
laughed. He made no answer. She came across to him, and with her little
fingers stroked his hair. She knelt down and pressed his hands to her lips. He
drew them away, and a shudder ran through him. Then he leapt up and went to the
door. “Yes,” he cried, “you have killed my love. You used to stir my imagination. Now
you don’t even stir my curiosity. You simply produce no effect. I loved you because you were
marvelous because you had genius and intellect, because you realized the
dreams of great poets and gave shape and substance to the shadows of
art. You have thrown it all away. You are shallow and stupid. My God! how mad I was
to love you! What a fool I have been! You
are nothing to me now. I will never see you again again. I will never think of
you. I will never mention your name. You don’t know what you were to me, once. Why,
once Oh, I can’t bear to think of it! I
wish I had never laid eyes upon you! You have spoiled the romance of my life. How
little you can know of love, if you say it mars your art! Without your art you're
nothing. I would have made you famous splended magnificent. The world would have
worshiped you, and you would have borne my name. What are you now? A third Ray
actress with a pretty face.” The girl grew white, and trembled.
She clenched her hands together, and her voice seemed to catch in her
throat. “You are not serious, Dorian?” she murmured. “You are
acting.” “Acting! I leave that to you. You do it so well,” he answered bitterly. She rose
from her knees and, with a pity I expression of pain in her face, came
across the room to him. She put her hand upon his arm and looked into his eyes. He
thrust her back. “Don’t touch me!” he cried. A low moan broke from her, and she
flung herself at his feet and lay there like a trampled flower.
“Dorian, Dorian, don’t leave me!” she whispered I'm so sorry I didn’t act well.
I was thinking of you all the time. But I
will try— —indeed, I will try. It came so suddenly across me, my love for you. I
think I should never have known it if you had not kissed me— —if we had not
kissed each other. Kiss me again, my love.
Don’t go away from me. I couldn’t bear it.
Oh! don’t go away from me. My brother No;
never mind. He didn’t mean it. He was in
Gest But you, oh! can’t you forgive me for
tonight I will work so hard and and try to
improve. Don’t be cruel to me, because I love you better than anything in the
world. After all, it is only once that I have not pleased you. But you are quite
right, Dorian. I should have shown myself more of an artist. It was foolish of me,
and yet I couldn’t help it. Oh, don’t leave me, don’t leave
me.” A fit of passionate sobbing choked her. She crouched on the floor like a
wounded thing, and Dorian Gray, with his beautiful eyes, looked down at her, and
his chiseled lips curled in exquisite disdain. There is always something
ridiculous about the emotions of people whom one has ceased to love cibil van
seemed to him to be absurdly melodramatic. Her tears and sobs annoyed
him. “I am going,” he said at last in his
calm clear voice. “I don’t wish to be unkind, but I can’t see you again. You
have disappointed me.” She wept silently, and made no answer, but crept
nearer. Her little hands stretched blindly out, and appeared to be seeking
for him. He turned on his heel and left
the room. In a few moments he was out of the
theater Where he went to he hardly knew.
He remembered wandering through dimly lit streets, past gaunt black shadowed
archways and evil looking houses. Women with horar voices and harsh laughter had
called after him. Drunkards had reeled by, cursing and chattering to themselves
like monstrous apes. He had seen grotesque children huddled upon
doorsteps and heard shrieks and oaths from gloomy courts. As the dawn was just breaking, he
found himself close to Covent Garden. The darkness lifted, and, flushed with faint
fires, the sky hollowed itself into a perfect pearl. Huge carts filled with nodding
lies rumbled slowly down the polished empty street. The air was heavy with the
perfume of the flowers, and their beauty seemed to bring him an anod for his
pain. He followed into the market and watched the men unloading their wagons A
white smoked carter offered him some cherries. He thanked him, wondered why he
refused to accept any money for them, and began to eat them listlessly. They had
been plucked at midnight, and the coldness of the moon had entered into
them. A long line of boys carrying crates of striped tulips, and of yellow and red
roses, defiled in front of him, threading their way through the huge jade green piles of
vegetables. Under the portico, with its gray Sun bleached pillars, loitered a
troop of draggled bareheaded girls, waiting for the auction to be over.
Others crowded Around the swinging doors of the coffee house in the
Piaza The heavy cart horses slipped and stamped upon the rough Stone shaking
their bells and trappings. Some of the drivers were lying asleep on a pile of
sacks Iris necked and pink footed the pigeons ran about picking up
seeds. After a little while, he hailed a handsome and drove home. For a few
moments he loitered upon the doorstep, looking round at the silent square, with
its blank close shuttered windows and its staring blinds. The sky was pure opal
now, and the roofs of the houses glistened like silver against it it From
some chimney opposite a thin wreath of smoke was rising. It curled, a violet
ribbon through the naker colored air. In the huge guilt Venetian lantern,
spoil of some Doge’s barge, that hung from the ceiling of the great Oak panel
hall of entrance, lights were still burning from three flickering jets: thin
blue petals of flame they seemed, rimmed with white fire. He turned them out and,
having thrown his hat and cape on the table, passed through the library towards
the door of his bedroom, a large octagonal chamber on the ground floor
that, in his newborn feeling for luxury, he had just had decorated for himself
and hung with some curious Renaissance tapestries that had been discovered
stored in a disused attic at Selby Royal. As he was turning the handle of
the door, his eye fell upon the portrait Basil hallwood had painted of him.
He started back as if in surprise. Then he went on into his own room, looking somewhat
puzzled. After he had taken the button hole out of his coat, he seemed to
hesitate. Finally, he came back, went over to the picture, and examined
it. In the dim arrested light that struggled through the cream colored silk
blinds, the face appeared to him to be a little changed. The expression looked different.
One would have said that there was a touch of cruelty in the mouth. It was
certainly strange. He turned around and, walking to the window, drew up the blind.
The bright dawn flooded the room and swept the fantastic shadows into dusky
corners, where they lay shuddering. But the strange expression that he had
noticed in the face of the portrait seemed to linger there, to be more
intensified even. The quivering ardent sunlight showed him the lines of cruelty
round the mouth as clearly as if he had been looking into a mirror after he had
done some dreadful thing. He winced and, taking up from the table an oval glass
framed in ivory Cupids, one of Lord Henry’s many presents to him, glanced
hurriedly into its polished depths. No line like that warped his red lips. What did it
mean? He rubbed his eyes, and came close to the picture, and examined it
again. There were no signs of any change when he looked into the actual painting,
and yet there was no doubt that the whole expression had altered. It was not
a mere fancy of his own. The thing was horribly apparent. He threw himself into a chair
and began to think. Suddenly there flashed across his mind what he had said in Basil hallwood
studio the day the picture had been finished. Yes, he remembered it perfectly.
He had uttered a mad wish that he himself might remain young, and the
portrait grow old; that his own beauty might be untarnished, and the face on the
canvas bear the burden of his passions and his sins; that the painted image
might be seared with the lines of suffering and thought, and that he might
keep all the delicate bloom and loveliness of his then just conscious
boyhood. Surely his wish had not been fulfilled? Such things were impossible. It
seemed monstrous even to think of them.
And, yet, there was the picture before him, with the touch of cruelty in the mouth.
Cruelty! Had he been cruel? It was the girl’s fault, not his. He
had dreamed of her as a great artist, had given his love to her because he had
thought her great. Then she had disappointed him. She had been shallow and
unworthy. And, yet, a feeling of infinite regret came over him, as he thought of
her lying at his feet sobbing like a little child. He he remembered with what
callousness he had watched her. Why had he been made like that? Why
had such a soul been given to him? But he had suffered also. During the three terrible hours
that the play had lasted, he had lived centuries of pain Eon upon eon of
torture. His life was well worth hers. She had marred him for a moment, if he had
wounded her for an age. Besides, women were better suited to bear sorrow than
men men They lived on their emotions.
They only thought of their emotions. When they took lovers, it was merely to have
someone with whom they could have scenes. Lord Henry had told him that, and
Lord Henry knew what women were. Why should he trouble about cibil vain She
was nothing to him now. But the picture? What was he to say of that? It
held the secret of his life, and told his story. It had taught him to love his own
beauty.
Would it teach him to loathe his own soul? Would he ever look at it
again? No; it was merely an illusion wrought on the troubled senses. The
horrible night that he had passed had left phantoms behind it. Suddenly there
had fallen upon his brain that tiny scarlet speck that makes men mad. The
picture had not changed. It was folly to think so. Yet it was watching him, with its
beautiful m face and its cruel smile. Its bright hair gleamed in the
early sunlight. Its blue eyes met his own. A sense of infinite pity, not for
himself, but for the painted image of himself, came over him. It had altered
already, and would alter more. Its gold would wither into gray Its red and white
roses would die. For every sin that he committed, a stain would fleck and wreck
its fairness. But he would not sin.
The picture, changed or unchanged, would be to him the visible emblem of
conscience. He would resist temptation. He would not see Lord Henry
anymore would not, at any rate, listen to those subtle poisonous theories that in
Basil hallwoods garden had first stirred within him the passion for impossible
things. He would go back to cibil Vain make her amends, marry her, try to love
her again. Yes, it was his duty to do so.
She must have suffered more than he had.
Poor child! He had been selfish and cruel to her. The fascination that she had
exercised over him would return. They would be happy together. His life with
her would be beautiful and pure. He got up from his chair and drew a large
screen right in front of the portrait, shuddering as he glanced at it. “How
horrible!” he murmured to himself, and he walked across to the window and opened
it. When he stepped out onto the grass, he drew a deep
breath. The fresh morning air seemed to drive away all his somber passions. He
thought only of syil A faint echo of his love came back to him. He repeated her
name over and over again. The birds that were singing in the DW drenched garden
seemed to be telling the flowers about her at chapter